<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints losse and lamentation A sermon preached at the funerall of the VVorshipfull Captaine Henry Waller, the worthy commander of the renowned martial band of the honourable city of London, exercising armes in the Artillery Garden. Octob. 31. 1631. By George Hughes Mr. of Arts, and preacher of Gods word in Alhallowes Breadstreet in London.</title>
            <author>Hughes, George, 1603-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13913</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104275</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840014</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840014</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4482</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03795)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4482)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1522:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints losse and lamentation A sermon preached at the funerall of the VVorshipfull Captaine Henry Waller, the worthy commander of the renowned martial band of the honourable city of London, exercising armes in the Artillery Garden. Octob. 31. 1631. By George Hughes Mr. of Arts, and preacher of Gods word in Alhallowes Breadstreet in London.</title>
                  <author>Hughes, George, 1603-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 [i.e. 54], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] B[eale] for Ralph Mab,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With an initial errata leaf; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>P. 50-54 are paginated 52, 53, 52, 56, 56.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Waller, Henry, d. 1631.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page_verso">
            <pb facs="tcp:4482:1"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS LOSSE AND Lamentation</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT THE FVNERAL of the VVorshipfull Captaine HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY WALLER, the Worthy Commander of the Renowned Martial Band of the Honourable City of London <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ lines">
                  <desc>〈1… lines〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:4482:1"/>
            <head>To the Right VVorſhipfull, the Preſident, Captaines and Gentlemen, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing Armes in the Artillerie Garden of LONDON, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Strength, and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Renowned Worthies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He honour which I beare you next my God, my King, my Church, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of ſome of you hath now forced this rude peece into pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view. I'le cenſure it, to ſave others the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, farre, unworthy of ſo many eares and eyes that it had and is like to have, and by my owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgement, once having the cenſure of the eare, it ſhould never have come to the ſecond of the eye; but others have paſſed it, and thus much I dare ſay for it, it is truth. The end of its comming to you is twofold; <hi>1.</hi> To minde you of your weaknes; death hath made a ſhrewd breach among you, and ſet upon you in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:4482:2"/>
               <hi>front,</hi> nor in the <hi>reare,</hi> and ſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke as the very <hi>body,</hi> not at the <hi>flanks,</hi> your chart is unwheeled, and your horſemen throwne; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your Captaine is taken off your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eads. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſoule is heavy while I ſpeake it. <hi>2.</hi> To repa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> your ſtrength, and there is but need of it, Mee thinkes I ſee <hi>Micaiahs</hi> viſion, <hi>the hoſt of Iſrael ſcattered as ſheep that have no ſhepheard;</hi> Should the hoſt of the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thus? Come and let me counſell you; <hi>Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Diſcenſion</hi> are enough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcatter an army, that lie as thicke at graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, as duſt into the wind; <hi>when Holines, Humility,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as walls a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, that they feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> force: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> accuſe you, but as my belo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you. Take heed that the unholy thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not found among you, walke humbly towards God and man, be not all Captaines, and love as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>keeping the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace;</hi> Then aske ioyntly of God a Captaine, and aske in faith, hee will appoint a man to goe before you in righteouſnes, courage, and the feare of the Lord. having thus to you, I would alſo, were I worthy, ſend a word about this matter t our Honoured Senators; Be ſure
<pb facs="tcp:4482:2"/>ye iudge for God in this great buſines, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it not your ſmalleſt Honour, if yee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing deny your ſelves for the glory of God, your Cities flower, and your countries good; al which lie ingaged in this deſigne. Theſe might I ſee effected, your Captaine, and your ſtrength revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, my God in both glorified, I ſhould have content enough, though many cenſures. For this I come forth, though I die, yet if the name of that Honoured head may live, whoſe praiſe with God is farre more glorious, though I ſuffer yet if ye may be the better and the ſtronger for it, it is my great reward. The care of this your ſtrength I ſhall ever commend to the Lord of Hoſts, he ſtrengthen you in righteouſnes, guard you with ſalvation, make you victorious by faith, and triumphant conquerors in his glory: In him I r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your hearty Orator, and fellow-Souldier in Chriſts Artillery, GEORGE HVGHES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4482:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4482:3"/>
            <head>THE SAINTS LOSSE AND LAMENTATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. King. cap. 13. ver. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>O my Father, my father, the charet of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His dolefull cry I heare but twice repeated in theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred hiſtories, and both times at funeralls. Firſt, this dying <hi>Eliſha</hi> himſelfe ſingeth this burden of lamentation at the funerall of his father <hi>Elijah</hi> (for it was his funerall, an heavy parting from his ſon,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4482:4"/>and from the earth, though with a more glorious tranſportation in a fiery charet by fiery horſes, and through a whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e-wind into heaven) his ſonne can doe no leſſe at this ſudden and admired change, than lament him, <hi>O my father, my father the charet of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 2.12.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, this honour had the ſame <hi>Eliſha</hi> at his change, when he was now ſicke unto death, from the mouth of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> an idolater indeed, but yet a King, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth himſelfe a ſonne alſo to the dying Prophet; and now comming to viſit his father in his ſickneſſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that death was ſent for him, and he muſt looſe him, hee weepeth over his face, and cryeth bitterly, <hi>O my father, my father, the charet of Jſrael and the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof.</hi> Heare it once more, and it is the burden of this dayes lamentation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther untimely, I hope, nor unſeemely; not untimely, for it's at a funerall; nor unſeemly, it being the funeral of ſo hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an head, by whoſe death I dare ſpeake it, I would we might not feele it, there is a charet unwheeled, and an horſeman
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4482:4"/>throwne this day in Iſrael. It is true here is neither King nor Prophet to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet a father of many ſonnes in as great a right as <hi>Eliah</hi> of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> or <hi>Eliſha</hi> of <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> ſuch as a fatherly reſpect hath made children, and want of this father hath made lamenting orphans; yet a man of God, a righteous ſoule zealous for the Lord of Hoſts, in whom God had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not a ſmall part of the Strength of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; blame us not then if we take up this lamentation, and cry, <hi>O my father, my father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words are the naturall notes of a burdened ſoule, and the bitter expreſſions of a mind oppreſſed, laid out by griefes peculiar<note n="a" place="margin">Apoſiopeſis.</note> Rhetoricke, outcries, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken diſtracted ſpeeches; O my father, my father; and there he ſtops, O the charet of Iſrael, and the horſe men thereof, and then he ſtayes; the mind doubtleſſe had ſomething elſe to vent, but griefe ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it, and the weeping paſſion will not let it out. My defence is from my text, if I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>be broken and confuſed, griefe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeake otherwiſe, and mournes like
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4482:5"/>ſuch ſermons beſt, whoſe companion and preacher I am at this time. Yet if y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire a fuller ſenſe of theſe diſtracted outcryes, and a more perfect reſolution of theſe broken ſpeeches, thinke my ſoule now to be in their ſoules ſtead, and let me perſonate a while <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhah</hi> to <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ah,</hi> or <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſh</hi> to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> not in his wickedneſſe, but his lamentation, and me thinkes, if geieſe would ſuffer me, I could tell you what they would have ſpoken. O my father woo is me, my ſoule is ſorely troubled for thee; Alas what ſhall I doe oh my heart, my heart aketh, and my ſoules e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ready to be powred out, I can have no reſt; for my ſtaffe is broken, and my father is quite taken away from me. O my father, What doe I ſtay behind for a poore forſaken orphan? O how happy ſhould I be, if death would doe me that favour as to bring mee now after thee? O my father, my father; or I would I onely had loſt a father and were a mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner alone, that I might yet finde others to comfort me; but on which ſide ſoever I looke, I ſee none but mourners, oh my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4482:5"/>heart is almoſt broken, All Iſrael laments and cryeth bitterly after thee, for their charets and horſemen are fallen, becauſe thou art departed from them: briniſh teares have beſmeared all faces, Iſrael Gods Church ſitteth as a deſolate wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and heavy burdens are ſounded in all her coaſts, woe is us, how is the glory of Iſrael this day decayed? how are her charets and her horſemen confounded? how is her ſtrength become feeble? for thou art taken from us. O my father, my father, <note n="a" place="margin">Melioripſi Iſrael eratin cratione ſua curribus &amp; equitibus. <hi>Calv paraph.</hi>
               </note> who wert a greater ſafeguard unto us then all the charets of Iſrael or the horſemen thereof: Oh thou ſtrength of Iſrael, our bowells are turned within us, we are ſorely grieved for thee!</p>
            <p>That wee may yet ſpeake more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably from the text, it will be good to ranke theſe out-cries into ſome method, though indeed griefe be ſo unruly, that it is no eaſie matter to keepe it in order; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe we will tye it up a little, and if we can looke with dry eyes upon the text theſe two things are obvious to our conſideration.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4482:6"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 The perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> produced in this mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſcene.
<list>
                     <item>1 The mourner <hi>Ioaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> King of Iſrael.</item>
                     <item>2 The bemoaned <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet now a dying man.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. The lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation it ſelf made over him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we read
<list>
                     <item>2 The manner of it in the doubled, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and diſtracted repetition, <hi>O my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my father!</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>1 The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was a 2. fold loſſe.
<list>
                           <item>2 <hi>Of a father, ô my father!</hi> Of the ſtay and ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>gth of Iſrael, <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> the Charet, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt the perſons here preſented in this mournefull act are <hi>Ioaſh</hi> the mourner, and <hi>Eliſha</hi> the ſicke dying and lamented fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as we looke upon them, and eye them more narrowly, wee will forget them in their more ſpeciall callings ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ioaſh</hi> to be a king, or <hi>Eliſha</hi> to bee a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4482:6"/>Prophet, this will be of no great uſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; more profit we may expect in the diligent view of their generall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according to the deſcription which the Spirit giveth of them. Of <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> who commeth downe to weepe over the face of this departing Prophet, we read,<note place="margin">2 Kin. 1 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>He did that which was evill in the ſſght of the Lord, he departed not from all the ſinnes of</hi> Ieroboam <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Nebat, <hi>who made Iſrael ſinne but he walked therein.</hi> What could bee ſaid worſe of a man? He was as wicked as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, it was his trade to ſinne, nay more, he was as bad as the worſt, a conſpiratour with that <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nebat</hi> the moſt abominable idolater that ever brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed on the earth. Of <hi>Eliſha</hi> againe, who lay now ſicke unto death and is here la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, we read,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 19 16.</note> he was the anointed of the Lord, on whom the Spirit of <hi>Eliiah</hi> was doubled after his departure,<note place="margin">2 Kin. 2.9, 10.</note> hee was a zealous champion for the Lord of Hoſts, a righteous ſoule, an heavenly Saint, and a deadly enemy to <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſinne and his idolatrous brood; yet this <hi>Ioaſh</hi> commeth to this <hi>Eliſha</hi> in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4482:7"/>his laſt ſickneſſe, weepeth over his face a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now departing, and cryeth after him i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this pittifull lamentation; O my father, my father!<note place="margin">Mat 11, 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> It is true that wiſedome is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified of her children, and as true th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God maketh her to be iuſtified of her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries alſo, even of them that hate her. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>1</label>
               <hi>The righteous ſoule departeth lamented, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, honoured by the very enemies of righte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> It is a ſtrange ſight to ſee the ſame man a murderer, and a mourner at the ſame funerall, or any one to lament that perſon upon the biere whom he hated to the death, and was ever reſtleſſe untill hee had layd him there, yet nothing more common between the righteous and the wicked. It is the crie of the ungodly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the inſt, while he liveth, kill him, ſtone him, away with him from the earth, he is not worthy to live; but when hee is dead indeed, the ſame mouth deſireth him, iuſtifieth him, ſurely this man was the Son God:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.27. 31, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Looke upon <hi>Ioab</hi> but in his treachery, hee hated <hi>Abner</hi> in his ſoule, he ſendeth good greetings unto him, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him aſide at his returne, ſmites him
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4482:7"/>and kills him, can yet expect him now before <hi>Abners</hi> hearſe, renting his cloathes, clad in ſack cloath, lamenting and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as a mourner? yet thus wee finde him.</p>
            <p>Who would thinke that <hi>Ioaſh</hi> ſhould be a mourner at <hi>Eliah's</hi> funerall, he a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirator with <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> this a righteous Prophet of the Lord of Hoſts? yet here he is, and weeps and cryes with a bitter mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, oh my father, my father! But why weepeth he? and how is it that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to doe the Prophet this honour at his death? Is it becauſe he loved him, as Chriſt wept over <hi>Lazarus?</hi> I dare not ſay ſo, no not ſo much as thinke ſo, that a man of <hi>Belial</hi> could ſo ſincerely affect a Sonne of God, and ſhould not queſtion it, but for ſome who are yet contrary min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.<note place="margin">An hic anime ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cere honoreus illum prophetae detulerit, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui in quaeſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uem vocant, &amp;c. Mihi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro fruſtra videtur que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, quandonen erat cauſa qus moveretur ad eſtentandum, <hi>Ioh. Wolph in tex,</hi>
               </note> It is therefore commented by one thus; Some doubt whether <hi>Ioaſh</hi> did this honour to the Prophet in his lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with ſincere affection, &amp;c. But it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me not worth the queſtioning, when now hee could bee moved by no cauſe to flattery.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4482:8"/>
            <p>Yet (with good leave) it ſeemeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to other pious and learned iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and I thinke upon better reaſon. Had <hi>Ioaſh</hi> beene in <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſtead, a dying man, I ſhould think, as the Author do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, there were then no cauſe of flattering, but <hi>Eliſha</hi> was now dying, and <hi>Ioaſh</hi> luſtie &amp; lively; and I doubt not, but an ungracious ſonne for a bleſſing or a portion may flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his father upon his bed of death, nay, ſooner then, when moſt unlikely to bee diſcovered. But not deſire his life as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> did; yea earneſtly deſire it, and bitterly bemoane the loſſe of it, if his ſafety and peace depend upon it, as the health of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> and his kingdome upon <hi>Eliſha</hi> did; there was then cauſe enough of flattery. The deſperate patient careth not for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay perhaps doth truely hate him, yet heartily deſireth his Phyſitian, loveth his phyſicke and his skill, and bemoaneth himſelfe when he wanteth them; he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not the man then, but he loves his owne life. Let <hi>Ioaſh</hi> looke upon <hi>Eliſha</hi> as a righteous Prophet crying down his ſin, and beating downe <hi>Ierob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ams</hi> altars, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4482:8"/>he cannot endure him, he hateth him to the death, yet when hee ſeeth him as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on whom all his dependance is, he earneſtly deſireth him; he loveth not <hi>Eliſha</hi> then, but he loveth his father, &amp; ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can I beleeve he weepeth for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loveth him, or that this lamen cation is from ſincere affection. Why then doth he thus bemoane him, and doe him this honour as to weepe over his face but at the thought of his funerall, while hee was yet alive? Negatively wee have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, it was not becauſe he ſo intirely lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, and poſitively wee now reply, theſe conſiderations might move <hi>Ioaſh</hi> or ſuch a wretch as he, to bemoane <hi>Eliſha's</hi> loſſe, or ſuch a ſoule as this.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Reason" n="1"/>
            <p>Firſt a partiall conviction of ſome good in the righteous ſoule commendable and deſireable by the very enemy, for howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wicked men are not ſo farre, nor ſo fully convinced of righteouſnes, as truely to affect it, and earneſtly to labour after it, yet ſuch a conviction there is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly which ſtops their mouths againſt it, and maketh them to wiſh for it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4482:9"/>when once they want it. It fareth as with the God of righteouſneſſe, ſo with the people of righteouſneſſe in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>His very eternall power and Godhead, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable things of him are ſo cleer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly ſeems</hi> by meere Naturaliſts;<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> yea by the whole world, that it is not grievous unto them to confeſſe him to be God, howbeit all this while they glorifie him not as God, nay,<note place="margin">ver. 21.30,</note> they are the very haters of God, ſo vainely are they convinced of a deity; yet againe when God is departed from them, and executes his iuſt iudgements upon them, they cannot but iuſtifie him in his proceedings, and bewaile themſelves for the loſſe of him when hee is gone: Such ſparkles of divine knowledge are left in corrupted man, and are kindled ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more by education within the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church: God may bee thus knowne by his enemies, but never ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourd or deſired before hee turne away in wrath and hide away his face in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, then <hi>Saul</hi> will ſeeme to honour him,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.25.</note> though erewhile his rebellion bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him for an enemy. Such entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4482:9"/>and eſteeme in the world have his ſervants likewiſe; as they partake of the goodneſſe of their God, to they doe of his uſage alſo amongſt men: Their piety, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, humility, and continuall ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of doing good convince the very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and force a confeſſion of their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; yet hate they them to the very death, though afterward their heart ſmite them, and when they are taken away, they cry for them, alas my brother! The Sonne of God fareth no better, his righteous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation doubtles convinced the world of his innocency. <hi>Pilate</hi> proclaimeth it before iudgement,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>What evill hath hee done!</hi> yet hee hath enmity in himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and to doe the Iewes a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he caſts him and condemns him; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe at his death he doth him this honour againe to proclaime his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <hi>I am innocent of the bloud of this iuſt perſon.</hi> Its ſtrange to ſee with what vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence and ravenous deſire of bloud <hi>Saul</hi> hunted <hi>David,</hi> he is convinced of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, yet he cannot love him, but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth him to the death, and after that hee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4482:10"/>had murdered him in his heart, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction driveth him to this confeſſion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>this thy voyce, my ſonne</hi> David? <hi>I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, returne my ſonne</hi> David,<note place="margin">1 Sam 26.27. 12, 25.</note> 
               <hi>I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more doe thee harme, I have played the ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red exceedingly. Thus precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.15.</note> and ſuch God maketh it to be in the ſight of men alſo. That wretched <hi>Balaam, that curſed</hi> ſorcerer confeſſeth this to the eternall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Saints, of whom he giveth no other commendation than to wiſh his ſoule in their ſoules ſtead,<note place="margin">Numb. 23.10</note> 
               <hi>Let mee dye the death of the righteous, and let my laſt and but like his;</hi> and yet who a more deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to their lives than he? This lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> upon <hi>Eliſha,</hi> might be forced by conviction, not invited by affection.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Reason" n="2"/>
            <p>Secondly, ſelf-love might reach him this mournefull note, himſelf was like to be the greateſt looſer by <hi>Eliſha's</hi> death and no wonder then if he make the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt lamentation. If we obſerve the ſtory, <hi>Ioaſh</hi> was at this time ſorely diſtreſſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Syrians; they had made the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4482:10"/>people of Iſrael in the dayes of <hi>Jehoahaz</hi> his father like the duſt by threſhing, and were yet domineering over them, <hi>Ioaſh</hi> had no great ſtrength leſt him of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to defend himſelfe or offend his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and now <hi>Eliſha</hi> is departing too, his father, his oracle for aduice, and counſell, his ſtrength and ſafeguard of himſelf and kingdome; the charet of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof were now falling, and now he and his people in all likelihood expoſed to the tyranny of the mercileſſe Syrians; can he love himſelfe ſo ill, think we, as not to mourne and weepe, and cry, O my father? A parallel no this we reade betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> a wicked King, and a righteous Prophet; <hi>Samuel</hi> may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the word of the Lord unto him, but <hi>Saul</hi> reiects it, and in his heart diſdaineth both the Prophet and his meſſage: he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth an enmity againſt God and him in his fleſh, and careth not how little hee ſeeth him, he being now his greateſt eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore: yet when <hi>Samuel</hi> is gone indeed;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.3.6. 14, 15.</note> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous diſtreſſe befalls him, and now hee wants him, Oh what ſhall hee doe for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4482:11"/>his <hi>Samuel?</hi> more worth were he at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> time than his crowne unto him; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he beſhreweth himſelfe, he honour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him and deſires him: nay when he was ſore diſtreſſed, the Philiſtines made wants againſt him, God was departed from him and anſwered him no more neither by Prophets, nor by <hi>Vrim,</hi> nor by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, then would he ſcrape <hi>Samuel</hi> out of his grave: yea rather than faile, he goeth to the divell for him, and when he ſeeth him he ſtoupeth, &amp; boweth himſelfe to do him honor, though in the event he was miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, worſhipping the divell, &amp; not <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel)</hi> yet all this while he loveth not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet but himſelfe. This honour have all Gods Saints,<note place="margin">Prov. 11.30.</note> that they be <hi>trees of life,</hi> not onely living themſelves, but alſo giving life and diffuſing their good whereſoever they come; &amp; though they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by-words and ſignes of contradiction, the very markes, whereat the ſcornes and ſcoffes of worldlings are bolted for their abode in this theatre, yet whence they are tranſplanted, they are miſſed, and wiſhed for, not for themſelves, but for the good
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4482:11"/>which followeth them. Selfe-love is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make a man act the friend, though otherwiſe in his heart he bee a deadly enemy, and ſo doe the wicked be-friend the godly, honour them and deſire them, becauſe they love themſelves.</p>
            <p>I have now but two words to ſpeake to each party, <hi>Ioaſh</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning king, and the lamented Saint, then they goe out, and we proceed.<note place="margin">Vſe 1.</note> Firſt I have a meſſage to thee oh king, not a dagger for a private ſtabbe, but a word to ſmite thee with in the open ſunne,<note place="margin">Iudg. 3.20.21.</note> even before the face of all Iſrael. Is this the voice of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> over <hi>Eliſha,</hi> O my father, my father? Whence learnedſt thou this note, thou painted Sepulchre? Doeſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire with the wicked againſt the Lord? content and delight thy ſelfe in <hi>Ieroboams</hi> life? and commeſt thou to be a mourner at <hi>Eliſhas</hi> death? God will iudge thee, thou curſed hypocrite. Oh how doth the fire of the Lord burne within me, and the zeale of the Almighty kindle againſt theſe wicked wretches? Woe unto you, ye vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous generation of hypocrites: what
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4482:12"/>make ye at the righteous mans ſepulchr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> what aileth you to rent your cloath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to walke in ſackecloath, to weepe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before his biere? Doe ye loath, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and hate his life? and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him at his death? Doe ye honour, hove, and deſire his end? yet his life and graces diſcommend? Doe ye build and paint, and guild his tombe? and yet your hands imbrued in his righteous bloud? ye are witneſſes againſt yourſelves;<note place="margin">Mat. 23.17.33</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſerpents, ye generation of vipers, how can ye eſcape the damnation of hell?</hi> For ye well deſerve it, that hate the God of righteouſneſſe, and his righteous ſervants, notwithſtanding ye are convinced, that ye ſhould glorifie him, and honour them, ye are your owne iudges, that your condemnation is iuſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">verſe 2.</note> I have an errand to <hi>Eliſhas</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, the dying Saint, and the righteous ſoule,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.10. Pſal. 37.37. Phil. 1.21.</note> and it is a meſſage of peace, Say un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the righteous it ſhal be well with him; his end is peace, and as his life was Chriſt, ſo now his death is his gaine. Comfore your ſelues then ye people of righteouſneſſe, ye holy nation: what
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4482:12"/>though for a while <hi>Balaam</hi> conſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, <hi>Shimei</hi> curſe you,<note place="margin">Num. 31.16. 2 Sam. 16.5. 1 Sam. 22.9. Act. 26.24. Ioh. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>Doeg</hi> accuſe you, ſlander you, <hi>Feſtus</hi> think you mad me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe ye are Chriſtians, and the world iudge you to death as the worſt of men not worthy to live; yet wait but a little, <hi>Balaam</hi> ſhall wiſh your happineſſe, <hi>Shimei</hi> ſhall bleſſe you, <hi>Doeg</hi> ſhall iuſtifie you, <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſhall bee convinced of your wiſedome,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.38.</note> and the world ſhall deſire you againe, of whom it ſhall not be worthy. Onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not your ſelves to <hi>Balaams</hi> conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie by ſinning and forſaking the God of righteouſneſſe; ſtand not ſtill, neither goe backe for <hi>Shimeis</hi> curſing; Feare not to walk with thy God for all <hi>Doegs</hi> ſlanders, Thinke not worſe of your ſelves for <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> his raſh iudgement; and fall not down before the wicked, though the world condemne you; Patience and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now become the Saints: Armed with theſe ye ſhall ſtand ſtedfaſt, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your God, and honour your ſelves in the face of all Iſrael; The eye which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you, ſhall bleſſe you, and the eare which heareth you ſhall give witneſſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4482:13"/>unto you nay yet farther, that very mouth that curſeth you, ſhall bleſſe you, that heart which hated you ſurviving, dying ſhall lament you, and that ſoule which abhorred you, ſhal deſire you again <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my brother, or as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> here cryeth after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>liſha,</hi> O my father, my father! This is the honour of Gods Saints, whoſe loſſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lamentation now follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O my father, my father!</hi> I have done with <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> this lamentation is none of his by right, his heart did never beget it, though his tongue had learned to ſpeake it; the is indeed <hi>Eliſha's</hi> owne, which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heavily at the parting with his father <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah,</hi> and is here taken up by <hi>Ioaſh</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe, but ſounds more harſhly from ſuch a iarring inſtrument. He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then from the Authours mouth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> how he acts it, we ſhall ſee the lively em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of a perplexed ſoule; though we heare the voyce onely, it is enough to make us conceive the dolefull geſture of the Actour, though we ſee no body; ſuch diſtracted outcries, oh my father, my father and then to ſtop; O the charet and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4482:13"/>horſemen; and to ſay no more, can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent no other ſhape unto us than torne cloathes; wringing hands, ſwollen eyes, beſmeared face, and ſobbing heart, a man full of ſorrow, and overburdened with griefe unſpeakeable. It is a woefull ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle to looke upon, and enough to moove a flint, that would but view it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, to weepe for company: and I confeſſe, it is not eaſie to forbeare while I relate it. That we miſſe nothing which may concerne us to make us fellow-mourners with this diſtreſſed ſoule, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation implyeth 2. things remarkable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The manner of it, It is doubled di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted and broken, the naturall ſymptomes of a ſoule overcharged with griefe.</item>
               <item>2 The matter of it, about which it was, a double loſſe.
<list>
                     <item>1 The loſſe of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>O my, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The loſſe of ſtrength, charet, and horſemen.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The manner is the doubling,<note place="margin">Repetitiveſt deloris oftenſie deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>paratione. <hi>Carthuſ, in 2 Reg. 2.</hi>
               </note> diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and abruptneſſe of theſe cryes, all undoubted notes of an unexpreſſible
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4482:14"/>griefe; and in relation to the matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ground expreſſed, it readeth us this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>2</label> The loſſe of the righteous is very grievous, and their lamentations very bitter. The ioy of the City is not ſo great, when it goeth well with the righteous, and they proſper: but their griefe ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth when they are cut off and taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.<note place="margin">Prov. 11.10.</note> It is true that when the wicked pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, there is ſhouting: but when the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man falleth, there is bitter weeping, doubled cryes, and pitifull exclamations, Alas our father, or our brother, we are ſorely diſtreſſed for thee. It may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> caſt in, <hi>Eliiah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> were famous Prophets in Iſrael, and this bewailing ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth rather to be for ſuch than for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men. To caſt this out againe as eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, It is confeſſed indeed, that the Prophets were accounted fathers in Iſrael, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed that they were thus lamented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Prophets; Righteouſneſſe onely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this honour, that the loſſe of them ſhould be ſo bewailed, whileſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophets die both undeſired and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamented. Dignities may command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4482:14"/>forced ſervice and a formall honour from inferiours, yet all this while they are a burden under which they groane, and die they may, yet be never miſſed, and not a mourner for them unles in a gowne or cloake. It is neither king nor Prophet, but righteouſneſſe that maketh the loſſe ſo heavy, and the mourning ſo bitter; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe bring their additions to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation; the loſſe of a righteous man, the City doth bewaile as a mother, the deceaſed child, who yet is comforted by her husband, that is better then ten chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto her, but at the loſſe of a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous King, or a righteous Prophet, ſhe ſits as a widow or as an orphan, rents her cloathes, teareth her haire, and cryeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, as a wife over her husband, or a poore child after its deareſt father, that cannot be comforted. It is true,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 14.19. 1 Kin. 1.22.37 Ierem. 22, 18.</note> when <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam, Ahab,</hi> or <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> wicked Kings were cut off, we ſee no great loſſe, and therefore we have no great lamentation, the City is quiet and no whit mooved, none cryeth ſo much as alas my brother!<note place="margin">1 Kin. 14.13.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ah, Ieroboams</hi> ſon, though a child,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4482:15"/>is lamented of all Iſrael, <hi>becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> found ſome good thing towards the Lord,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when good <hi>Joſiah</hi> falleth, Ieruſalem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth wringing her hands like a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> widow, and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> and al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bitterly after him:<note place="margin">2 Chr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.35.24 25.</note> yea ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it is, that unto it the Prophet makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> al o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Convents mourning, <hi>It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> us the mourning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Megiddo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, 12.11.</note> where that good King <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> was ſlaine. When <hi>Hananiah, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Amaziah,</hi> falſe Prophets die, all is ſtil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is no wailing for them, nor mention <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, unleſſe to curſe them, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is eaſed of a tedious burthen with them but when <hi>Samuel, Eltiah,</hi> or <hi>Eliſha</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.1. 2 King. 1.12. 2 Kin. 13.14.</note> heaven heareth the ſighes and ſobs, and groanes of mourners, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bemoane the loſſe of theſe, oh our father our father! Once more, when a curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Shimei,</hi> or a wicked <hi>Shebua,</hi> or a churli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nabal</hi> are cut off, there is no miſſe of them nor weeping for them: But when an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Abuer,</hi> or good <hi>Barzillas,</hi> or a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Imathan</hi> depart, their funeralls hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> troupes of mourners, and many ſad cryes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4482:15"/>after them, Ah woe is me!<note place="margin">2 Lam, 3.33.38.</note> 
               <hi>Dei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Abner <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dyeth?</hi> Alas, <hi>there is a great man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this day in Iſrael:</hi> Or els,<note place="margin">2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5, 26.</note> 
               <hi>O</hi> Ionathan <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the high places, I am diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, my brother Jonathan.</hi> All this depends upon the ſucceeding matter, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the lamentation about which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all theſe cryes are not about nothing, but there is a father, or a charet, or horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men fallen, for which theſe pitifull excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations are doubled: In the text, the whole matter of the lamentation fell un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a twofold conſideration, Good <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither as a father to <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> or els as the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret and horſemen of all Iſrael; the loſſe of theſe may deſerve a woefull lamentation, and becauſe they lie in this ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the precedent mourning,<note place="margin">Flebat loas de lens ſe ac regula ſuum tanto pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trono privend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie deſtituen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, tam ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſsimo &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diliſsimo mox cariturum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore, prophetae, ac patre. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſ in tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> I ſhall lay them downe in their order the ſufficient grounds thereof, and then cloſe up al with a uſefull application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O my father: my father!</hi> Blame not the mourner, if you heare him paſſionate, it is his father whom he bewaileth, the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the relation, the more ſenſible the loſſe, and more heavy needs muſt the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4482:16"/>be.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Whileſt I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> father,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or brother, or friend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it may touch my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and perhaps my heart too so farre as to bid my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, I am ſorry for it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> over; but when my friend, my brother, my father it taken off my head, I the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſtroake, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mourne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was <hi>Shiah</hi> to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> blow which cuts off the father, cannot but make the childs heart doe, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>3</label> if it cry, O my father, my father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are the righteous, even fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and places of their abode: needs muſt the City then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that fatall ſtroak which cuts them a ſunder; and when they ſmart, it is likely we ſhall heare them cry, and weepe bitterly,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.1.</note> unleſſe that heavy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have befallen them, that no man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to heart, when the righteous periſheth.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Question"/>
            <p>But upon what ground hath <hi>Ioaſh</hi> this relation to <hi>Eliſha?</hi> was it not from his calling, that he was a Prophet, rather then from his righteouſneſſe that hee was ſo good? whence then is this relation given to the righteous? or he might be a father
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4482:16"/>to <hi>Ioaſh</hi> onely; how then ariſeth it, that the righteous are ſuch to then Cities?</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Response"/>
            <p>To anſwer theſe quaeries, and to cleare the truth. Firſt, that Prophets had the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation of fathers it is not doubted, falſe as well as true might be ſo called by their baſtard brats (as the Romiſh ghoſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are at this day by thoſe whom they have begotten to be limbes of Antichriſt, and children of perdition) and yet be ſuch fathers whom the children may bee bound to curſe for the inheritance which they have left them, but have little or no cauſe to weepe and bemoane the loſſe of them. <hi>Gray heads alſo are fathers, and a crown of glory, much to bee honoured, if it be found in the way of righteouſnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prev. 16.31.</note> Righteouſnes onely addeth this to the Prophet, that it maketh him a deſired father: Kings, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Magiſtrates that ſpeak and rule in righteouſnes are more properly indeed the nurſing fathers of Kingdomes and Churches, yet can it not be denyed but a poore wiſe man alſo may proove the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter father of the City; and ſo all the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the righteous, if not ſo properly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4482:17"/>called fathers, yet are they in very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> relation, brothers and faithfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> friends, and brothers may be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of fathers, <hi>and a friend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Prov.</hi> 18.24. whoſe loſſe cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heavily afflict the City, and make them mourne. Againe, though <hi>Eliſha</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> called father of <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> yet of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> as a king who ſhould be the father of his ſubject, nay of <hi>Iaoſh</hi> as a wicked king, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Eliſha</hi> father of his kingdome alſo; and ſuch are the righteous to their habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, yea to the very wicked alſo. But how doth <hi>Eliſha</hi> proove himſelfe to been father? Surely in theſe three particulars, though not in all to <hi>Ioaſh</hi> himſelfe, yet to ſome ſoules in Iſrael, 1. In Generation, 2. In Counſell. 3. In Providence; as the righteous alſo doe unto their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Reason" n="1"/>
            <p>Firſt, he was a father in generation, I meane, not naturall, but ſpirituall, by which he begat, though not <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> yet others doubtles to be the ſonnes of God; and theſe ſticke ſo cloſe, that when God ſtrikes their father off their head, they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4482:17"/>weepe bitterly indeed, and are hardly comforted. This honour God doth to his Saints on earth, that though the Spirit onely beget again to God, yet the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is called the father. It is Saint <hi>Paul</hi> that claimeth this of his Corinthians; <hi>Though ye have</hi> 10000 <hi>inſtructers in Chriſt yet have ye not many fathers;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 15,</note> 
               <hi>for in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus have I begotten you through the Goſpel.</hi> Primarily God thus honoureth his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and miniſters of the Goſpel, yet not exempting any Chriſtian from this inſtrumentall begetting againe to God; [<hi>viz.</hi> by their private Chriſtian admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and inſtructions, &amp; their godly life] which doubtleſſe maketh a moſt neere tye betweene the ſoule begetting, and the ſoule begotten, that will not bee looſed without bitter mourning.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Reason" n="2"/>
            <p>Secondly, he was a father in counſell, and that to <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> though it tooke but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle effect with ſuch an ungracious ſonne; yet he leaveth not to do it upon his dying bed; He adviſeth <hi>Ioaſh</hi> to ſhoote the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of the Lords deliverance, and hee ſhootes, to ſmite the Syrians and hee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4482:18"/>ſmites, but very fooliſhly, onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the man of God was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with him.<note place="margin">Gen 45.8.</note> Such a father did God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> and ſuch maketh he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> righteous to their neighbours: they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> counſellers for the peace and good of them among whom they live; and this maketh a knot not eaſily broken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out groanes.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Reason" n="3"/>
            <p>Thirdly, he was a father in his carefull providence for his ſonnes ſafety and his kingdomes ſecurity. It was a worthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which he left behind him; had his ſonne had ſo much grace as to have made good uſe of it; and other precious bleſſings, no queſtion, he left to him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther children, which kept the witneſſe of a loving father <hi>Ioſephe</hi> providence proves him a father indeed, which kept <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Court, and his kingdome, and his neighbours alive through ſo many yeeres of famine. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> notes it as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of fathers,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.14.</note> by which alſo he deſireth to approove himſelfe to his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> I will not bee burdenſome unto you, though I am your father, for the children
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4482:18"/>ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children; and ſo he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay up many a prayer, and many a bleſſing for them, which they were yet ignorant of. So do the righteous alſo proove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves fathers, by getting many good bleſſings together temporall and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and leaving them behind to many naughty children which they little thought on, leſſe fought for; It is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able therefore when Iſrael grieved the Lord, and <hi>Iudah</hi> oft times provoked him yet he ſhewed mercy unto them, and did them good, for his covenant with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> their fathers, who had intreated him long before: and this muſt needs ſo unite them to their poſterity, that they cannot bee divided, but even their heart ſtrings cracke beeing overbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with ſorrow, becauſe they are not To ſumme up theſe parcells in one, and uſe it, as it is an argument to inforce theſe lamentations at the iuſt mans funerall. If the breach that God made upon <hi>Vzzah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.7.</note> a ſervant of the family troubled all Iſrael, and made <hi>Davids</hi> heart ake; alas what
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4482:19"/>trembling and mourning ſhall there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when God ſhall cut off the friends, the children, the brethren, the fathers of it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have a father cut off from the head of a child, none knowes the loſſe, but an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, and hee can bewaile it, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſenſe of the breach of that naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> betweene them: and ſpirituall orpha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can doe no leſſe, their loſſe being no wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> inferiour, thus the very thought of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fathers departure,<note place="margin">Act, 20, 37, 38.</note> maketh Saint <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſian children to make great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, they wept ſore, and ſorrowed much to thinke they ſhould ſee his face no more. To looſe a faithfull, wholeſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailour, a carefull provident father, on whom ones life depends,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is no ſleight iudgement, no ſmall loſſe, and therefore deſerves no little lamentation: Such are the righteous, ſuch their loſſe, and ſuch may wee expect ſhould their mourning be. This is the firſt part of the burden, the ſecond followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O the charet of Iſrael and the horſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> thereof.</hi> This is the very ſting of the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and it pricks to the heart indeed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4482:19"/>Iſrael was now like to loſe her charet, and her horſemen, and then lying open to the mercileſſe tyranny of the Syrians, could expect nothing but bloudy maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, and woefull deſolation;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> oh what a bitter lamentation doe we thinke would be in the coaſts of Iſrael, when crueltie breathed forth nothing but death, and there could be no reſiſtance? The vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar reading ſhall not ſtay mee <hi>(the charet of, Iſrael and the driver thereof)</hi> though it be a faire occaſion for the Cardinals cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt gloſſe <hi>(a charet to carry Confeſſours, and a Dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver to pricke on the ſluggiſh cattle.)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Currus Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum ſupper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetione, Auriga diſcreta pigr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſtimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one; quaſi ſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo blandae exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationis. <hi>Hug. Card, in tex.</hi> In hebras ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrus Iſrael, &amp; mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eius, <hi>i.e.</hi> potentior ad defenſionem Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael quam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia cum cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus bellicis. <hi>Ex Rab. Sal. citat Lyra in 2 Reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.</hi>
               </note> It liketh me better to keepe cloſe to the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, and that <hi>Lyra</hi> confeſſeth it to bee more conſonant to the Hebrew text (the charet of Iſrael and the horſemen or ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, or the Artillery thereof becauſe he was more for the defence of Iſrael, than their military troupes with warlike cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets. Having this helpe from an adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, we ſhall not ſtick long in ſearching for truth here: It is cleare in hiſtories both ſacred &amp; profane, what ſtrength of people ancient time placed in charets, and how
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4482:20"/>weake they accounted themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out them;<note place="margin">Ioſh. 17.16.18</note> The children of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore fearefull to encounter with the <hi>Canaanites</hi> in the valley,<note place="margin">Iudg. 1.19.</note> becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> charets of iron; and <hi>Iudah</hi> could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> drive one the inhabitants of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe they had charets of iron; The whole ſtrength of Syria for the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſiſted in theſe warlike inſtruments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> king of Canaan with theſe terrified the children of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Iod. 4.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Xenoph.</note> for he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets of iron. In ſucceeding time Iſrael learned this ſtrength of theſe nations, and they make charets alſo to ioyne battel with their enemies:<note place="margin">1 Kin. 10.26.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> had a thouſand and foure hundred charets, and twelve thouſand horſemen,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 22.34.</note> and <hi>Ahab</hi> dyed in his charet at <hi>Ramoth Gilead:</hi> Happy had it beene for them if they had not put too much confidence in this ſtrength. The ſame were in great account with the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of Aſia and Africa; and as theſe, ſo horſemen were in little leſſe eſteeme, of whom we reade two ſorts were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in uſe.<note place="margin">Equites cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſti,</note> Some were ſo covered and overclad with armour, that, as <hi>David</hi> in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4482:20"/>
               <hi>Saul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> harneſſe, they could ſcarcely move with it, unfit for any exploits of activity, and yet of good uſe to breake rankes and diſorder the battell, and put the enemy into a confuſion: Others were of lighter burden, more nimble &amp; active for fight,<note place="margin">Equites levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris armatura.</note> and theſe were the ſpeciall and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ine combatants, by whoſe agility or heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the honour of the field moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly was either got or loſt: ſo that in a pitcht field or a place capable of their march, a great army of foot have beene accounted weake without them. In ſhort, charets and horſemen have been thought the very ſinewes, and ſtrength of States, and Kingdomes; ſuch was this holy man of God to Iſrael, the very pillar &amp; ſtrength of Church and nation; blame them not then if they ſo heavily cry after him. Such honour likewiſe have all Gods Saints; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>4</label> The righteous are the chiefeſt ſtrength of Church and Kingdome, whoſe they are, and amongſt whom they live. It is a doctrine which the heavenly Preacher readeth from his owne experience.<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.13.14, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>This wiſedome J have ſeene under the ſunne, and it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4482:21"/>ſeemed great unto me: There was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and few men within it, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great King againſt it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> built great had works againſt it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> found in it a poore wiſe man, and he by the wiſedome delivered this City, yet no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſame poore man; Then I ſaid, wiſedome is better then ſtrength.</hi> A concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very firmly gathered from the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; ponder we them a little, and we ſhall ſee it. <hi>Salomon</hi> giveth us this not as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon obſervation, but as a thing notable and very remarkeable above moſt things in his experience, the benefit and yet the neglect in the world of this godly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which is our righteouſneſſe, or the feare of the Lord, <hi>It is great unto we.</hi> And it deſerves no leſſe than a ſerious note, marke we but the oppoſition <hi>(I here was a little City)</hi> and <hi>(a great King came againſt it, &amp;c.)</hi> this no ſmall diſproportion, againe <hi>(there were but a few men within it)</hi> and yet <hi>(he built great bulwarks againſt it)</hi> this was greater, and little hope could the City have to ſubſiſt long upon ſuch unequall tearmes; yet now in this great improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of ſafety <hi>(there was found in the City
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4482:21"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poore righteous godly wiſe man)</hi> and hee defeateth this <hi>great king and his great bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, he delivered the City,</hi> not by wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of warre, but by <hi>his wiſedome.</hi> or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes; therefore however the world eſteem of it, the wiſe Preacher concludes, wiſedome is better then ſtrength, or it is the ſtrongeſt defence of all; this hath its undeniable truth, whether we reade it as a parable, or an acted hiſtory. In the map which the Prophet draweth of <hi>Iudah,</hi> Gods holy place, hee thus deciphers the ſtrength of it,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26, 112, 3, 4</note> 
               <hi>We have a ſtrong City, ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will God appoint for walls and bulwarkes;</hi> and what ſurer defence than <hi>Safety it ſelfe?</hi> its Canon-proofe and a wall impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? but who the inhabitants? <hi>Surely the righteous nation which keepeth truths entreth in</hi> and dwelleth there, <hi>and their Iehovah is their rocks of ages, or everlaſting ſtrength.</hi> This is very ſtrange, and who almoſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth it? may a man aske, where lyeth this ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon</hi> in the righteous? their faces promiſe as little or leſſe than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason </seg>
               </label> It will not betray them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it: it ſtandeth mainly in their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4482:22"/>with God through Chriſt, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it were poſſible for the world to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, they would become weake, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> other men; but whileſt this laſteth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> theirs, heaven is theirs, they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of angells for their aſſiſtance, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more punctually, their ſtrength is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in theſe particulars.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            <p>Firſt in the power and wiſedome of their Captaine, their reconciled God; his counſell ſhall ſtand though all the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels</hi> in the ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h conſpire againſt him, and his power is irreſiſtible, though all the kings of the earth bandy themſelves to fight with him; and how ſafe muſt the holy ones be,<note place="margin">Prov. 18.10.</note> when hee is their Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? <hi>The name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous runneth into it and is ſafe, or ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft;</hi> free from gun ſhot, where they may ſit and laugh, and the enemy cannot hurt them. This tower goeth with them whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever they move, where they abide, the very name of that place is,<note place="margin">Iehovah Sha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mab, <hi>Ezek, 48.33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Lord is there;</hi> and in whomſoever the ſtrength of Iſrael is, they muſt needs be a ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and guard to their City, their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4482:22"/>Church and ſtate.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            <p>Secondly, in the ſpirituality of all their forces and munition, whereby they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and grieve the enemy, yet are not diſcerned, that they ſhould bee avoided, or repelled: Their Captaine is a Spirit, and therefore mocketh his enemies in his intermination of the perfidious Iewes; <hi>Wee unto them that goe downe to Egypt for help,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 31.1.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtay on horſes, and truſt in charets, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are many, and in horſemen, becauſe they are very ſtrong, but they looke not to the holy one of Iſrael, neither ſeeke the Lord: yet hee alſo is wiſe and will bring evill, and will not call backe his word; but will ariſe againſt the houſe of evill doers, and againſt the help of them that worke iniquity; Now the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are men and not God, and their horſes fleſh and not ſpirit, when the Lord ſhall ſtretch forth his hand, he that helpeth ſhall fall, and he that is holpen ſhall fall downe, and they all ſhall faile to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> For there can be no reſiſtance, a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit fighteth againſt them, and alas they cannot ſee either to offend him or defend themſelves. Againe, their ſouldiers and miniſters are ſpirits,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.7.14.</note> the Angels which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4482:23"/>ſerve them,<note place="margin">2 Kin. 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> and are for guard about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one of them went out in a night and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the camp of the Aſſyrians an hundr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> foure ſcore and five thouſand men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was never perceived; It is a pittifull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be ſmitten, and never know whence the blow commeth, help or defence can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee had againſt ſuch an adverſary. Once more their weapons are ſpirituall, and therefore cannot bee warded off faith and prayer powerfull inſtruments, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the weakeſt women have beene the greateſt conquerours:<note place="margin">Heb. 11.34.</note> 
               <hi>Through faith</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle witneſſeth the righteous <hi>haue put to flight the armies of the aliens,</hi> or forrei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> enemies; this is a ſure weapon which they were never able to ſtrike out of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers hand, and this was his victory, or conquering peece.<note place="margin">Ezod. 17.11, 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 13, 14, 15.</note> By prayer alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> kept off the blowes of <hi>Amalek</hi> from Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and gave them a fatall overthrow; ſo that God commands him to write it for a memoriall in a booke, not onely the conqueſt but the meanes and weapon which <hi>Moſes</hi> doth, and erecteth alſo an altar, whoſe name he called <hi>Iehovah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:4482:23"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lord my banner,</hi> as a pillar for the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall memory of faithfull prayer. In this the Paraphraſt put the ſtrength of <hi>Eliſha, Thou art better by thy prayer to Iſrael than charet or horſemen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melior erat Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratioratione ſua, &amp;c. <hi>Cald. Paraph</hi>
               </note> Spirituall forces are thus irreſiſtible, therefore they are very ſtrong; and ſuch is the ſtrength of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">3.</note> in their unexhauſted proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which continually maintaineth their ſtrength, that they need not feare a decay thereof. The righteous alwayes pitch by that <hi>little river, whoſe ſtreames make glad the City of God;</hi> of which,<note place="margin">Pſal 46.4.</note> though they bee faint and weary, if they doe but drinke, their ſtrength returnes as <hi>Sampſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 15.19.</note> and they grow mighty and ſtrong againe. This river is no other, but the water of life, the word and Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, it is meate and drinke to the beleeving ſoule; and if he chance to faint, hee getteth ſtrength from thence to his faith, and if his hands grow feeble, he drinketh, and ſtretcheth them forth againe mightily in prayer; and ſo long as he is able to winde his weapons, his ſtrength will bee unreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4482:24"/>Happy that City, that nation, that Church, that hath ſuch mighty men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> champions, their ſtrength is admirable, and they ſhal not be aſhamed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the enemy in the gate. Such ſouldiers, ſuch champions, ſuch walls, ſuch bulwarks are the righteous to their places, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion then is neceſſary, their loſſe muſt be very grievous, and their lamentation deſervedly very bitter. I have now but three words to ſpeak to <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> to Iſrael, and to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> to the wicked to the Church, and to the righteous, and I cloſe with the text.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Ioaſh</hi> thou art a mourner at <hi>Eliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> death,<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but who, thinkſt thou, will lament at thine? The righteous indeed fall, and the City is mooved, all cry after him, and the ſtreets ring with their lamentations; but the wicked are cut off, and all is ſtill, they are neither miſſed, nor deſired, nor lamented. We will not croſſe he proverb, yet may we limit it,<note place="margin">Eccl. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>So dyeth the wiſe man, even as the foole;</hi> ſo dieth he indeed for the nature of his death, his ſoule is ſeparated from his body, but not ſo for the manner,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4482:24"/>iſſue, and conſequents of his death; hee dyeth a wiſe man, but this a foole, he like a Saint expecting to riſe againe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but this as a beaſt which periſheth for ever, he dieth and is loſt as a pearl, this and is never miſſed, like carrion, he is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away and bitterly lamented, but this is cut off, and not ſo much as deſired. Will ye ſee how they uſe him when he is gone? It was <hi>Iehoiakims</hi> caſe ſonne to <hi>Ioſiah</hi> king of Iudah, a wicked wretch whom God thus curſed, when he was dead.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier. 22.18, 19</hi> Non plangent eum vae ob fratrem meum, vae ob ſororem, non plangent eum, vae ob re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, vae ob reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eius; Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut proiiciunt cadaver aſini, ſic proiicient cadaver eius, lacerabitur &amp; proiicietur, ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra portas Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. <hi>Calv. paraph.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They ſhall not lament for him, ſaying, Ah my brother, or ah ſiſter, they ſhall not lament for him, ſaying, Ah Lord, or ah his glory, He ſhall he buried with the buriall of an aſſe, drawne and caſt forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the gates of Ieruſalem.</hi> Reade here and ſee your doome, ye generation of evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, though ye be the ſonnes of kings and children of Princes, yet your iniquities make you ſtinke, ye die and are dragged, and tumbled out like carrion; this is your ſentence from heauen. It is the curſe of folly to be buried like an aſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> O Iſrael how art thou behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Eliſha?</hi> Thy child indeed; yet thy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4482:25"/>father, thy guide, thy counſellour, thy charet and thy horſemen, thy ſinewes, thy very ſtrength and ſafety: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this why doeſt thou not love him? oh how would I weepe over thee with Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalems lamentation? O Iſrael, Iſrael, thou that keepeſt the oracles of God, and calleſt thy ſelfe by the name of his Church, why art thou weary of thy righteous Princes, thy righteous Prophets, thy righteous ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and righteous people? thou ſeemeſt not to regard though they be perſecuted, killed, and ſtoned; oh that thou wouldſt conſider in this thy day the things which concerne thy peace, before they bee taken from thine eyes; thy peace, thy ſafety, thy ſtrength is in thy righteous members, &amp; doeſt thou ſo ſlight them, while thou now inioyeſt them? Woe is thee, thou wilt be feeble when they are gone, then ſhalt thou weepe bitterly, and they will not be. How is it that thou art become unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall? thou forſakeſt thine owne, and thou harboureſt ſtrange children: can ſalvation be thy walls, when unrighteouſnes and oppreſſion are among thy rulers, profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4482:25"/>among thy Prophets, ſtrange altars in thy temples, and idolatry in thy habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations? Alas thy leanneſſe, thy leanneſſe! thou art become weake and feeble, and thy deſtructions are now upon thee. Were I worthy to counſell thee (yet I may call to thy remembrance Gods counſell unto thee) O that righteouſnes might abide &amp; rule in thy habitations, that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ingrave it on thy Nobles, on thy Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, on thy Prophets, on thy Captaines, and on thy Souldiers, that in thee might dwell only a people of righteouſnes, then ſhouldſt thou be as the ſtrong City which the Lord hath founded, ſalvation ſhould be thy wals, the name of <hi>Iehovah</hi> thy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, thy rereward, and thine everlaſting ſtrength; thou ſhouldeſt be built as on a rocke that can never be ſhaken, and be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed as mount Sion, Gods holy place, which ſhall never be remooved.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, is <hi>Eliſha</hi> among the ſicke,<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and maimed, and cripples, and feeble? what doeſt thou heere <hi>Eliſha?</hi> How commeſt thou thus tyred and weak and faint, thou righteous ſoule, thou ſtrength of Iſrael?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4482:26"/>haſt thou bin dallying, &amp; playing the wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in the harlots lap? are thy locks ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, oh Sampſon? and haſt thou betrayed thy ſtrength into the hands of thine enemies? Haſt thou loſt thy Captain, thy Aſſiſtance, thy weapons? where is faith now? where is that Almighty praier that openeth and ſhuts heaven, that calleth for legions of Angels? Alas thou haſt ſinned, &amp; thy God is hidden from thee, and thy confederates dare not come neere thee, thou canſt not hand before the enemy, nor wind a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon for thy defence; thy ſtrength is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come weaknes, and thou haſt made thy ſelfe a ſcorne to the adverſaries, whom thou haſt ſometimes wounded? Shouldſt thou thus tempt God and fall? this is thy rebuke; yet let me adviſe thee too. Come ſhelter thy ſelfe a little under the wing of thy redeemer, ſtay there while thy locks are growne, thy Captaine will come that way, then lay hold on him, thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces goe along with him, gather them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, draw out thy weapons again, and begin to uſe them, let faith pitch it ſelfe upon thy God through thy Chriſt, tell
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4482:26"/>him, thou wilt throw thy ſelfe upon his power, and faithfulnes to preſerve thee, let thy prayer ſet upon him mightily, and give him no reſt, untill hee come againe, and renew tſty ſtrength like the Eagles. Then comfort thy ſelfe (oh thou charet of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof) the eyes of all Iſrael are upon thee for their ſtrength, thou mighty man of God, they weepe with bitter lamentation when thou art taken from them, and ſhouldeſt thou quaile for any adverſe power? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thy ſtrength, thou haſt power to combat with hell and overthrow it, to grapple with death, and to defeat it, to make the grave tremble, and open unto thee, that thou maiſt ariſe againe &amp; come forth a conquerour. Death may humme about, but it is a drone, it hath no ſting, ſinne may make a bluſter, but it hath no ſtrength, hell may belch foorth great words, but it is already vanquiſhed to thy hand, and the grave may threaten much, but it can doe nothing againſt ſuch a mighty man as thou art; thou haſt now nothing to doe, but reſting in <hi>Jehovah</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4482:27"/>thine everlaſting ſtrength ſit downe and ſing; <hi>Death is ſwallowed up in victory, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> death where is thy ſting? oh grave or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> where is thy victory? The ſting of death is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law; But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be to God, who hath given me victory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now done with my Text.</p>
            <p>I miſtooke, I have not yet done, I muſt have one curſory more over it for this heavy and ſad occaſion, then I cloſe up indeed: yet the corrupt cuſtome of our dayes maketh mee almoſt afraid, when men of corrupt minds, enemies to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and children of their father the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell muſt bee made Saints at their fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, and though all their life time they have beene tracing downe to hell, yet at their death they are poſted from the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit in a charet into heaven, but it is a windy one that breaketh in pieces, and lets them fall downe againe, before they come halfe way thither. Nevertheleſſe, I ſee the holy Fathers have uſed to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of the graces of the Saints deceaſed,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4482:27"/>and to ſpread their names as a ſweet oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among their brethren, and it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry commendable, if faithfully perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and not abuſed to paint divells; with this care I ſhall proceed by Gods helpe to performe this laſt duty for this honoured brother, and it muſt bee with care: for there are two eyes upon me very extreamely oppoſite, Envies and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that, would have nothing ſaid, this perhaps too much; I ſhall not feare to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe either, ſo I may pleaſe my God, by whoſe bleſſing I now begin, You will pardon mee if I keepe not the common method, to begin from his deſcent and parentage though that of worthy and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ranke, not to be neglected (if I ſhould keepe that order;) but me thinkes, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>proper praiſe from anothers worth,<note place="margin">Sedgenus &amp; proav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; quae non f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sus ipſi vix ea noſtra voc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I deſire to let him have his owne, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, where he commeth within my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as a righteous ſoule, and nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere certaine than that he was borne a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. His transplantation therefore into this City is my beginning,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Richard Stocks.</note> and his fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full growth under the labours of a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb facs="tcp:4482:28"/>Miniſter now with God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> gave full teſtimony, that he was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of righteouſnes indeed; thence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up to ſhew forth the power of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the places private and publicke whereunto God called him.</p>
            <p>He was a righteous husband, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no more of this, leſt I provoke bitter la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation. He was a righteous maſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ſervants feele it, from whoſe heads, God hath taken off their maſter this day. He was a righteous father, not to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> alone, they are too little to have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of it, but to orphans and fatherleſſe was he father, a guide, and counſellor; my owne loſſe is with theirs, beare with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> if in the ſenſe of it I bewray my infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; as <hi>David</hi> for his ſonne, O my father, my father, would to God I had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thee, O my father, my father! Hee was a righteous friend to many, I give but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> inſtance of it, his reconciling difference almoſt every day, his hands were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ever out of an arbitration, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> without partiall reſpects to any that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him a iudge over them, I know I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4482:28"/>many witneſſes to this, who now want him.</p>
            <p>In his more publike offices, hee was firſt a righteous ſouldier ſquared by Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> rule, hee would doe violence to no man, nor put any man in feare;<note place="margin">Luk. 3.14.</note> in this condition he tooke a good degree, he was a Captaine and a righteous Commander; the vertues of a Commanders maieſty, wiſedome, meeknes and love ſurely made him one; diſorder, as there muſt bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſouldier ſometimes, could never make him paſſionate; hee was a man of ſuch admired moderation, He croſſed the rule of that raſh commander, <hi>(Jt is folly to intreat, where a man hath power to compell)</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heſiod p. 41.</note> He found it better governing by love: this made the flower of the Cities, yea, of the kingdomes Artillery, ſo unanimouſly ſubiect to his command. Let me minde you (ye worthy ſouldiers) know ye not that God hath taken away your Captaine from off your heads this day? and can yee doe leſſe than cry after him <hi>(O our charet and our horſemen?)</hi> I know ſorrow hath fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led your hearts; yet, by the way let mee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4482:29"/>adviſe you, be not overcharged, that you forget your calling; but when yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weepe over this your honoured head, and lamented before his hearſe; Ah our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ah his glory; wipe your faces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and to worke againe for God, pray for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> double portion of his ſpirit upon ſome of your brethren, and chooſe him, who may goe before you in wiſedome, and courage, and the feare of the Lord.</p>
            <p>I am now at a ſtand, <hi>An arma, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cedat? whether he were better ſouldier, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Citizen?</hi> His wiſedome, his courage, and his impartiall carriage in the City affairs, which might concerne him, beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that he was not onely a good man, but a good Citizen; his worth provoked the City,<note place="margin">Quid in illa virtutum, quid, ingenii, quid ſanctitatis, quid puritatis invenerim ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dicers, ne fidem creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ex ceda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; tihi mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem delorem intutiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordanti quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caru e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. <hi>Hier. Mar. ep. tem, 1.</hi>
               </note> not only to call him to her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon counſell, but to deſigne him to a more honorable place in the High Court of Parliament, where he manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a righteous ſervant to his King to his Country, and to his City, I muſt ſtay, leaſt (as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writes to <hi>Princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of Marcella a widow) if I ſhould tell all, I ſhould either ſeeme to hyperbolize, or
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4482:29"/>oppreſſe your hearts the more; when ye ſee what a great good ye have loſt. In this honour for his laſt time he lived, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Ye may expect now in my hand a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of good deeds: but I have none, the reaſons theſe. 1. It was his his care to give to God in his poore and in his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, the portion of his eſtate while he lived; yet dying he hath given as well as living. 2. It was his mind not to have a trumpet ſounded at his death, and I ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill it. I muſt leave him, he will be gone; it was my portion to commend his ſoule in the laſt breath into the hands of his faithfull redeemer; and his body I muſt commend to the earth, in the aſſuted hope of his ioyfull reſurrection; Onely two things I would commend to you, and then your ſelves to God. 1. The honour of his name, let it be as a ſweete ointment among you in everlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membrance; he was your ſtrength, your charet and horſemen. 2. The imitation, his righteouſnes, his wiſedome, his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courage; ye ſee his reward, he is now with God at reſt, his worke is done: our houre 
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
